So here's where we're executing the insert query and the AddPost function.
هنا نقوم بتنفيذ استعلام .الإدراج ودالة AddPost
And now if we change this to just have a comma and a tuple after here,
وإذا قمنا بتغيير هذا لتوفير فاصلة ومجموعة عناصر بعد
after this percent s, and make sure to have enough parentheses,
&rlm;s&rlm;%&rlm;&rlm;) والتأكد من وجود) ،أقواس كافية
we should have a forum that's safe against the SQL injection attack.
فسيكون لدينا منتدى آمن .ضد حقنة هجوم SQL
Let's try it out.
.فلنجرب ذلك
And here's a test post that has a single quote in it, and sure enough,
ها هو منشور اختبار يحتوي على علامة اقتباس مفردة
that worked.
.ويعمل بنجاح بالتأكيد
Let's try the attack query again.
.فلنجرب استعلام الهجوم مرة أخرى
Single quote, paren, semicolon, delete from posts, semicolon, dash, dash.
علامة اقتباس مفردة، قوس دائري، فاصلة منقوطة،&lrm; .delete from posts، فاصلة منقوطة، شرطة، شرطة
And this time, we're successfully treating that as just text and
وهذه المرة، نتعامل بنجاح مع ذلك على أنه مجرد نص
not a piece of SQL.
.وليس جزء من SQL
Awesome.
.رائع
With that simple change, we foiled one of the most infamous security holes
من خلال ذلك التغيير البسيط، تصدينا لواحدة من أشهر الثغرات الأمنية
a database-backed web app can have.
.التي يتعرض لها تطبيق ويب معتمد على قاعدة بيانات
Just remember that whenever you execute an insert query,
يجب تذكر أنه في كل مرة تقومون فيها ،بتنفيذ استعلام الإدراج
make sure to use query parameters instead of string substitution.
تأكدوا من استخدام معلمات الاستعلام .بدلاً من بدائل السلسلة
In case you forget,
،وفي حالة نسيانها
here's what the Psycopg 2 documentation has to say on the matter.
إليكم الوصايا المذكورة في Psycopg 2 .بشأن تلك المسألة
Warning, never, never, never use Python string concatenation, plus, or
فهي تحذر من استخدام ربط السلسلة في لغة Python وهي علامة زائد أو
string parameters interpolation, percent,
استنتاج معلمات السلسلة وهي علامة ،بالمئة
to pass variables to an SQL query string, not even at gunpoint.
لتمرير المتغيرات إلى سلسلة خاصة باستعلام SQL .ولا حتى عند التهديد
And they give the same format that we just used.
وهي توفر .التنسيق نفسه الذي قمنا باستخدامه للتو
Now personally, I don't think we really need to have documentation that tells us
إنني شخصيًا لا أعتقد أننا بحاجة إلى وثائق تخبرنا
what to do at gunpoint, but we all do have a right to secure code.
بالأمور المطلوبة عند التهديد، وإنما .من حقنا جميعًا أن يتوفر لدينا تعليمة برمجية آمنة